<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the late iourney of the Iesuites, banished out of the kingdomes of Bohemia and Hungaria</title>
            <title>Relatio nuperi itineris proscriptorum Jesuitarum ex regnis Bohemiae et Ungariae missa ex Helicone juxta Parnassum. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856485</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856485</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22038</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04415)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22038)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1313:19 or 1313:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the late iourney of the Iesuites, banished out of the kingdomes of Bohemia and Hungaria</title>
                  <title>Relatio nuperi itineris proscriptorum Jesuitarum ex regnis Bohemiae et Ungariae missa ex Helicone juxta Parnassum. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Eld],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Relatio nuperi itineris proscriptorum Jesuitarum ex regnis Bohemiae et Ungariae missa ex Helicone juxta Parnassum.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 1313:20 (identified on film as STC 14537a) has variance: A3 misnumbered B3.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Bodleian Library and in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1313:19 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and 1313:20 (Bodleian Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Czech Republic --  Bohemia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Hungary --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22038:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22038:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION <hi>OF</hi> THE LATE IOVRNEY of the IESVITES, <hi>BANISHED</hi> Out of the Kingdomes of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:22038:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22038:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF the late Iourney of the Ieſuits baniſhed out of the Kingdomes of <hi>Bohemia, and Hungaria.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ame (as I ſuppoſe) hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declared how all the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> were ſent and bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out of the Kingdomes of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungaria,</hi> that they might neuer at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to come againe into thoſe Kingdomes hereafter: and this baniſhment of theirs was after this maner, that if any of thoſe <hi>Ieſuits</hi> be found in the two fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Kingdomes, whereſoeuer, with whom ſoeuer, of what condition ſoeuer he be; and vnder what pretence ſoeuer; according to the definition of the Statutes of either Kingdome, he ſhould pay the iuſt reward of his fact. The poore wretches are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that neither interceſſion, nor any way deuiſed by art or friend ſhould preuaile to bring them in againe for euer. Now I come to their going out, why doe they goe? Being once conſtrained to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; they went away willingly, <hi>bona voluntas non eſt agitanda calcaribus,</hi> a willing mind needs not the ſpur. Conſtrained ſay you? namely, they would
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22038:3"/> depart for the time of anger willingly. This ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and caſting forth of them, although it brought exceeding much greefe and ſorrow to their whole Society, euen as that ſame Bore ſent by <hi>Diana</hi> into the corne of <hi>Callidonia:</hi> yet did it not altogether caſt away the ſpeare, but rather fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed that ſame moſt Godly ſentence, <hi>(when they ſhall perſecute you in that City, fly into another.)</hi> But who doe you aske? this was their recreation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by theſe wretched ſtudents diſtinguiſhed the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of their ſtudies.</p>
            <p>They doe too too much earneſtly thinke that they are to ſearch into theſe cares, where they may recouer a ſecure, and (as I may ſay) a healthfull place; ſuch as they had left at <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia:</hi> and ſee, the euent was contrary to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
            <p>While they went thither in this <hi>Bohemian. Hungarian</hi> baniſhment, that at length they might embrace faire <hi>Germanie,</hi> they come, they ſee, they ſalute their fellowes and bretheren. O <hi>Germanie,</hi> how great a wonder wert thou to theſe baniſhed men at there firſt entrance, how diddeſt thou yeeld an allurement to thoſe greedy eies! they ſee the goodneſſe of the land: it is moſt wonderfull and remote from all danger: they ſee the temper of the aire; it is moſt wholeſome. There is all ſound and perpetuall healthfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſpeake of the floriſhing fields, the high hills, and the vnhurtfull chaſes? I will not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22038:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpeake of the little brookes ſliding with a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant brinke, and the ſtately kinds of woods and groues. Theſe, theſe ſeemed to the Fathers the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> moſt full of a pleaſant ſweetneſſe: the very midnight, which is wont to bee pleaſant to all, they made vnquiet to themſelues. And what would it bee (ſay they) if ſo pretious fleeces of ſheepe, ſo many fertill Cities, villages and mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; and ſo good great a plenty of corne, oliues, and vine-yards ſhould appertaine vnto vs? Oh brethren, let vs make tryall, let vs vſe our beſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: that wee may be receiued firſt in <hi>Germanie:</hi> afterwards that wee may become Lords of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ô <hi>Germany,</hi> how thou ſtrikeſt without a bruiſe, how thou woundeſt without blood! how quickly and louingly thou doeſt drinke to theſe Fathers the cups of their deſire and wiſh! how thou ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt on them! O brethren, theſe men about to touch the matter to the quicke, doe put on them (as they are wont,) the prepuce of impudency; they ſolicite faire <hi>Germany</hi> with earneſt and daily intreaty; that it would afford them a moſt ſafe defence againſt theſe clouds of baniſhment.</p>
            <p>They cry out, thou ô <hi>Germany</hi> art the onely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, which art able to preſerue this company, to chaſe away ſtormes amongſt the waues and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts. <hi>India</hi> would moſt bountifully defend vs; neither would <hi>Italy</hi> deny vs any thing: but it is an exceeding long iourny thither; here the aire is moſt dangerous, that which way ſoeuer we turne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22038:4"/> vs, an exceeding great burthen of this difficulty is laid vpon vs.</p>
            <p>We haue no ſmall cauſe to reſide elſewhere: but now ſeeing our paſſing ouer hath a little taſted of this land (in which theſe that are addicted to our fellowſhip doe not liue in want) we conclude, that this thing is not done without the diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Alſo this <hi>Germany</hi> being better knowne through a proceſſe of time, hath deſerued to be a longer time loued of vs; and is accounted worthy to be adorned with the garland of our piety, and moſt faithfull inſtructing. Walke ouer and ouer it. O <hi>Germany,</hi> what is it, that our ſo many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies doe watch in thy townes and houſes for thy ſafety? other lands being let goe, wee deſire thy helping hand, ô <hi>Germany</hi> (ſay they.) Let the holy Scripture moue thee; <hi>Succour the needy:</hi> Let it mooue thee, that thou maiſt follow mercy; <hi>excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe mercy.</hi> Neither doe we requeſt any great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor things too high, onely ſome monaſteries in which we may haue meate, drinke, and apparrell. In theſe monaſteries we will liue religiouſly; we will ſhew our deuotion and loue towards <hi>Germany;</hi> and alſo our eſpeciall care in inſtructing youth. And we, and others with vs ſhall fly with theſe winges, and ſhall exceed all humane matters. In the meane time although our innocency ſhall bring vs into a narrower roome and fame, yet ſhall it fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine through all the coaſts of <hi>Germany;</hi> and ſtaine <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> vnleſſe they become better.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:22038:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Of which their wonderfull faire perſwaſion after that the brethren had made an end; the Lords the Delegates of <hi>Garmany</hi> not long meditating, at laſt doe anſwer thus. Neither doe they diſſemble that they alſo are ſtirred and heated with that ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely heat. We haue beene very attentiue to your requeſt (o Fathers): Alſo we haue attentiuely heard (as is fitting) your cauſes and reaſons, prouoking vs to prouide you ſettled places amongſt vs, which truely haue beene acceptable to vs. Wee would that our anſwere to you be plaine and without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. For that you extoll our beautifull Country, <hi>Germany,</hi> with all kind of prayſes, we doe take it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably: onely this wee diſlike, that you deſire to reſt with vs in this boſome which is proper and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to ours. And truely we do very much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that you do not ſeeke out and deſire other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces fuller of our miracles. For although the ayre might be moſt dangerous in <hi>Italy,</hi> by your ſaying, perhaps it might bee more temperate in <hi>Spaine,</hi> where there be more of your companies; and more of your brethren. Yea there you haue your <hi>Meca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> himſelfe, who as a <hi>Minerua</hi> doth preſerue you on water, and as an <hi>Vliſſes</hi> doth defend you being in danger of life.</p>
            <p>Doe you ſay that the iourney into <hi>India</hi> is too long? It is ſhorter into <hi>France,</hi> where (if your apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy may bee beleeued) your companions are of late preferred with new priuiledges. If you haue there ſo good opportunities, why doe you ſtriue to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22038:5"/> forgoe them? Doe you ſay it will be good for vs, hurtfull to you, to profit vs by your piety and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in our ſtudies? It is not expedient for you (ô Fathers) if yee determine any thing to bee done of you in our right. And if we be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <hi>Germany</hi> hath more certaine aſſertions of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to thinke well, then <hi>Trecenſis</hi> heretofore in <hi>France</hi> (which is commonly called <hi>Troy.</hi>)</p>
            <p>But we doe exceedingly maruell what the cauſe ſhould be, why in ſo ſhort a time ye ſhould bee caſt out of ſo many ſtately common-wealths and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes? Truely all their fields are large bookes, which we cannot thruſt vpon you by turning them, but for conference ſake onely ſhew them as true to the whole world, and of you as yet not refuted We deſire that ſome of you would behold your acts done in <hi>England: Certainly the acts of</hi> Garnet <hi>and of all of you would breath out ſome other thing then Innocency:</hi> namely, treaſon, and innouation, of which you were all guilty.</p>
            <p>This one thing you obiect, (ô Fathers) but know this, a deepe wound retaines a ſcarce: Yee did not bid farewell to the <hi>Venetians</hi> againſt your wills; but perhaps vnconſtrained.</p>
            <p>You had neuer gone away by the decree of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Lords, had not the commandement of <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth Pope cauſed you, to whom being the head of the Church, you yeelded all humble obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience with due obſeruance: and in this intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Religion you adored his Surplice: <hi>So obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22038:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> alone is the vertue which worketh the other vertues in the minde: and what were it of ye ſhould call him Lord, Lord, and would not doe what he ſaith?</hi> Ah how impatient were the <hi>Venetian</hi> Lords of your departure? How willingly would they haue detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you longer, if good words, honours, if more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer new priuiledges could haue preuailed any thing.</p>
            <p>But in ſayling we muſt giue eare to our Pilot, in warre to our Captaine: <hi>So that fidelity due to the Pope by the Venetian title hath made you wretched men baniſhed.</hi> It is written: <hi>He that beleeueth ſhall be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We now talke alone (ô Fathers Ieſuits) and are weakned: we could wiſh that a <hi>Venetian</hi> were here who might affirme theſe things.</p>
            <p>We do adde nothing heere but what your ſelues had in your Apology: that the will of God may be done, who is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; from whom as you expect ſaluation, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo expect iuſt iudgement. We do willingly paſſe ouer with ſilence the <hi>Belgicke</hi> fame, declaring what reproachfull things, contentions and wicked deeds you haue there committed: If in others there bee any diſgrace and wickedneſſe, in you it is prayſe and comelineſſe (as it is in your Apology.)</p>
            <p>We know not what to ſay, onely this wee hold, that God liueth, who cauſeth his Sunne to ſhine vpon the good and bad, and raineth vpon the iuſt and vniuſt, and will reward euery one according to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22038:6"/> his workes: VVe do alſo willingly paſſe ouer, why wee ſaw your honeſt company baniſhed out of <hi>France</hi> for their faults: wee are full of writings to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>In briefe, ye are accuſed of treaſon and ſlaughter intended againſt Kings: whoſe life and blood how you laid in waite for, would haue beene manifeſt (more cleare then the noon day) had not that ſame <hi>Carmelitane</hi> worke couered it vpon your Martyrs. Hereupon a Catholike within theſe three yeares (if I be not deceiued) obiected fairly vnto you that you teach and write commonly, that any man of what condition ſoeuer hee bee, may and ought to kill or ſlay a King (ſuppoſe any King you will) for a certaine ſtipend or penſion of mony, if hee bee a Tyrant, or diſobedient to your will and ſayings.</p>
            <p>This is your practiſe whereby you preuaile much with bad men: whereupon you deſeruedly worſhip <hi>Henry Garnet,</hi> as a Martyr for that his wicked and ſauage deed, who for it was executed in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>VVee ingeniouſly confeſſe that which is proper to all <hi>Garmans,</hi> that our Gallowes, Iibbets, priſons and all inſtruments of torture, are full of ſuch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
            <p>Let vs not cheriſh a thought of the feyned and lying miracles of ſuch moſt falſe martyrs. We do euen tremble (as God ſhall help vs) that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique religion ſhould couer ſuch Barbarous, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage, and moſt diuelliſh facts; and that it can call
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22038:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> and worſhip ſuch wicked and filthy men as Saints. So much euill was religion able to perſwade. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were the winds the cauſe of their expulſion out of thoſe moſt famous Cities of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> (we will not ſpeake of <hi>Polonia,</hi> and <hi>Swetia:</hi>) Theſe things ſhall neuer be forgotten, ſo long as that winged charriot of Fame ſhall paſſe through countries and ages. Yea haue beene ſhunners of peace and concord: yea haue brought in diſſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, braules, and treacheries into theſe kingdomes. All theſe you doe vnder colour of religion; as that your practiſe wrought by moſt fraudulent wiles, and moſt wicked attempts doth witneſſe. This is it by which you wring your ſelues into high places; you flatter the eares of the chiefeſt men; being moſt skilfull in that matter: And ſo you couer your indirect going and ſitting amongſt theſe Peeres with the mantle of religion and piety (with a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.) We alſo vnderſtand (ô fathers vnleſſe you haue ſome other religion then the Catholike) that you alſo, after your manner doe attempt the ſame: iuſt after the manner of Sorcereſſes; which while they can doe no harme to others, doe hurt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>Amongſt theſe excellent Eſtates of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, you bring in alſo an innouation: where thoſe ſame good Catholiques are Atheiſts, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and ſimple men, they are commonly called: yee doe all for this end, that treacheries and braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings might be brought in, whereby you might fiſh
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22038:7"/> in ſafety for your company. And truly, not the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> and <hi>Hungarians</hi> onely, but euen your Catholikes, from elſewhere doe obiect the fame things vnto you. Where we certainly ſuppoſe this to be in the better part of you; grant vs ô Lord to ſpeake forth peace in our times: All the turmoiles which you cauſe (your accuſers alleadge) are made for religions ſake (vnder this colour you affect your monarchy amongſt the Catholikes;) yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they muſt not be ſaid to be vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the profeſſors of the Goſpell at any time, for the cauſe of religion: O miſery; we ſuffer not our ciſterns to be drawne for all, whom we vnderſtand you runne into.</p>
            <p>For to what end is that plenty? But aboue all we ſet before vs the preſent eſtate onely of the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians.</hi> The ſeducers of the common people, ſay, that here is no talking of religion: ô blindneſſe! Let them beleeue that will; they ſhall finde to their owne coſt, that religion is our beginning, middeſt, and end: by which all things done, or to be done, are ruled; or rather in which they are all contained, your following, ſeuere, and harſh proceedings with <hi>Cloſtargrab</hi> and <hi>Braunaro</hi> ſhall afford you one liuely example of ſixe hundred.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Emperour <hi>Matthias</hi> wrote very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely in his late letters to the Earle of <hi>Bucquoy;</hi> Thou ſhalt deſerue excellently well of vs, of out Princely houſe, of religion, and of the Common-weale; if thou wouldeſt admit of this religion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22038:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ô <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and wouldeſt entertaine friendſhip with the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> thou couldeſt not haue warre: The <hi>Pope</hi> would bleſſe thee; the <hi>Spaniard</hi> would ſalute thee, and all the whole Clergy would viſite thee. But all theſe things ô Fathers, are vaine; vnleſſe more weighty matters be behind. For yee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime and condemne all for Heretiks, which doe not obey the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, and yee teach open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that no credit is to be giuen to them. In the meane time yee ſtirre vp the Peeres of this Realme one againſt another by your diuers waies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes: yee ſow diſcord betweene the magiſtrates and the ſubiects; and by your vnſpeakeable ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty yee cauſe variances in this Empire. By which your deceiptfull ſtratagem yee haue ſhewed your companions to be moſt deceiptfull; that your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are eſteemed as rotten nuts; yea a ruſticke honeſty is better than this your learned malice.</p>
            <p>You promiſe all things vpon oath, but in the end you keepe none. And good reaſon: for what religion doth bind them to the law, whom their owne religion and the <hi>Popes</hi> Bull doe free from all bonds of Law? You make a politike mixture of thoſe things which belong to the honour of God and his word, by ſaying; As though conſcience were not ſo much to bee kept in politicke matters. Doe not we know theſe things (good men) we do altogether thinke with him, That there is no greater deceipt in all iniuſtice then is in them, who then, when they moſt deceiue,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22038:8"/> doe it, that they may ſeeme to be good men. And truly, they ſeeme moſt ſtrange to vs enquiring, why faith amongſt the Ieſuits ſhould want followers: Afterward it was told vs that it was prouided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you long agoe by a ſpeciall edict, that any man may prouide for other good men by his laſt will; that faith cannot be ſaid hereditary. All the true profeſſours of the Goſpell in the Sacred <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Empire ſhall for euer endanger their liues and ſafety vnleſſe they be carefull, prouident, and watchfull in theſe and ſuch like matters. Good God, was it poſſible that theſe things ſhould come to our cares?</p>
            <p>Beleeue it (ô Fathers) euen your inſtruments and meanes by which you doe theſe things; much more your wicked deeds themſelues are knowne to vs.</p>
            <p>You haue Sermons; this is a great matter; which like a canker ſpread abroad: by which alſo you ayme at the end of the Oratour, which is, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, and draw others into his owne opinion. To theſe are added your actions and moſt ſtrange va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riations in your behauiours and carriages, by which you allure the wayward common people; which do become the ſeller of victuals a iuggler or baud, beter then they become a Pulpet. As the Trecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian iudgement in <hi>France</hi> is of Father <hi>Binet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither haue you Sermons onely (ô Fathers) but confeſſions alſo, this is greater: by theſe the condition of euery priuate houſe, and of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22038:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> goodmen of the houſes, the ſecrets of the whole common-wealth or Kingdome, where you liue; yea the ſecrets of the Romane Empire and their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are knowne to you. By theſe (we ſay againe) you deſeruedly domineere ouer the conſciences of men, and by compelling whom you will to vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things, you moderate all things by your owne reaſon: becauſe it is written: VVhoſe ſinnes you ſhall remit, they are remitted; and whoſe ſinnes you retaine, they are retained.</p>
            <p>By this place iniuſt contracts are made with you, commandements, or wicked and turbulent coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes are inioyned with a gentle buzzing, things iniuſtly gotten are kept ſtill: loues and vnlawfull mariages are not onely not broken off, but often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are contracted: In a word, the court is kept here.</p>
            <p>To theſe truely (that I may ſpeake with you) pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netent men may bee compelled by the prieſt. For neither was power granted in vaine to the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors by Chriſt, as well to binde as to looſe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (ô Fathers) this is your chiefeſt deuice: you haue two ſorts of diſciples here; all for your owne vſe and profit: one of them, murtherers of heretique Kings and Peeres, as you call them. whom you neuer ceaſe to incenſe and animate with all diligence and care, as alſo with promiſes of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting perpetuall glory, and of eſcaping Purgatory. Who can here reſiſt ſo many armed men?</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22038:9"/>
            <p>The other ſort of your diſciples are the ſonnes of great men, whom while you teach ſo, that when the perfection of wit in them ſhall come at length to the top and height of knowledge, you ſo binde vnto you, together with their parents, that you may haue ſufficient by the helpe of theſe, wherewithall you may liue, and encreaſe your companies and religion. You inſtill Logike and Rhetorike into them, that they may be Sophiſters. This, that they may defend any doubt, perſwade falſe things, and open the doores to your companions amongſt all men. There the truth is ouerwhelmed with deceiptfull diſtinctions ſophiſtications, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations, and mentall euaſions; here it is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with a trimneſſe of words, and with a <hi>Ciceronean</hi> eloquence. <hi>And I gaue my heart</hi> (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>that I might know Wiſdome and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and my Errours and folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not to omit the diuinity, which we heare that you reach, you haue a ſingular methode there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, (as becommeth ſingular men) by which all of your teaching doe expound the Bible philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and Philoſophy like Diuinity; ſo that <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> may feed on the flower of their youth, Sathan may rightly challenge to himſelfe the reſt thereof.</p>
            <p>O good Ieſu, how theſe wicked men doe pretend with their Atheiſme thy moſt holy name to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all mankind? But what boldneſſe and raſhneſſe is it of yours (ô Fathers)? wee will not ſay impudency, that you ſhould come out of the Pulpit
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22038:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> (which was beſtowed vpon you in <hi>Bohemia,</hi>) into the Court, and attempt to adminiſh the weight and worth of his Maieſties letters, by a diuerſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, and wreſted explication of the words? that you read <hi>Elias Donat, Catoes</hi> Diſlikes, the <hi>Compendium</hi> of Logicke, or the <hi>Epitome</hi> of Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke: when yee diſputed the Letters not confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Pope; wreſted from <hi>Rodolphus,</hi> by the vrging &amp; conſtraining of the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> that you taught the ſum of Phiſicks, the extract of Metaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiks, a breuiary of the whole world; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſaid that theſe letters were not ſubſcribed of all: Loe wee ſweare vnto you, that you had ſtill remained in your reſt and quietneſſe, if omitting theſe publike, you had conteined your ſelues in your owne priuate matters, and in the meane time (being ſo buſied) had better indoctrinated the children: So it falleth out as often as any tranſgreſſeth the limits of his profeſſion, and ſo, I know not by what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny he is iuſtly puniſhed for his curioſity: <hi>Nature hath giuen to all men to be happy, if any knew how to vſe it.</hi> VVho alſo had this ſaying, <hi>Let euery one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine within his owne fortune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, O Fathers, you haue drawne to you wonderfull goods: and that you might be ſtill dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more wealthy, you were come to that height, that leauing your prieſtly function, you were not aſhamed to intrude your ſelues into the ſecular go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. Hereupon you are proclaimed the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerters of the common good, the enemies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22038:10"/> of the kingdome, which cuſtome of yours ſeemes very feeble. For the Kings of the gentiles beare rule: and they which haue power ouer them are liberall: But you not ſo, it is your part not to reigne, but to vſe the rod, and to ſhake the feruloe within the territories of your kingdome. This we thinke belongeth to you (ô Fathers) that wee may ſpeake truely. It is one thing to weaken, another thing to entreat, this belongeth to you. It is one thing to obey, another thing to command; that belongeth to you. It is fitting to keepe prieſts in the ſtate of humility and obeyſance. We (ô good Fathers) but that you goe in an outward ſhew and title of holineſſe, which hath a ſhadow of vertue; would by theſe relations call your vile company, wicked, adulterate, to whom it is pleaſant to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue: they had rather haue a great name, then a good name: while they cannot be knowne by their vertues, they deſire to be knowne by their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. The end of your actions doth declare that, which is, to bring in ſubiection not onely theſe two Kingdomes, but the whole <hi>Romane</hi> Empire; yea all the whole world to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Romiſh</hi> bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:22038:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> YEa it is not the leaſt amongſt the greeuances of the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> for which you are driuen out of that Kingdome, namely that by your helpes and perſwaſion truce is made betweene the <hi>Turkes</hi> and our men: onely that the ſtrength of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> might be kept whole and ſound for the rooting out of all Heretikes (as you terme them) out of <hi>Gremany.</hi> And hereupon you ſtirre vp a Biſhop elſewhere in the City, that he would build a fortreſſe or tower, to the hurt of his potent neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and to the diſprofit of all profeſſors of the Goſpell. The loue of the <hi>Dublines</hi> elſewhere kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth no meaſure amongſt the counſailers, whom you diſgrace and ſtaine with a <hi>Portugallike</hi> libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Whereupon one profeſſor of the Goſpell is exceeding miſtruſtfull to another: and although they ſeeme to encline to friendſhip, we know not what hand oftentimes doth cauſe contention. O ſtrife, ô cruell ſtrife; ô ſtrife ſprung from the furies and hell it ſelfe. All excellency of true profeſſours of the Goſpell is by you troden downe, and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Authors of diſcord) is come to nothing. This (ô Fathers <hi>Ieſuites</hi>) is your crafty deuice; by which you might giue from hand to hand the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Romane</hi> Empire to the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Spaniard</hi> as perpetuall dictatours, but that <hi>Mercury</hi> the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of ſleepe had lately (although too too late) ſtirred vs vp.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:22038:11"/>
            <p>This is your end; who can hope for better meanes by which you atchiue your end? <hi>Lucius Mummius</hi> taking <hi>Corinth</hi> reſerued not ſo much as an halfpeny to himſelfe of ſo many ineſtimable ſpoiles: you doe not thirſt after our goods, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, but euen after our very blood. Your letters proclaime this, your plots and ſtratagems in <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mataw,</hi> and elſewhere doe proclaime it. For your auncienter wickedneſſes in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> are odious vnto vs. Haue you not yet heard how ſome blood-ſucker of your owne order in the yeare of our Lord, 1582. ſpake? but that we knew it was one of the Emperours houſe, we ſhould haue ſworne it had bin written in <hi>Caucaſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>How Germany may ſafe be held,</l>
               <l>Take my aduiſe (thou Reader mild:)</l>
               <l>O Caeſar vſe thy power, the ſeruants all of Luther,</l>
               <l>With ſword, with wheel, with ſea,</l>
               <l>With ropes, with fire, eke bemurther.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wee tremble to repeate your filthy <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits (which is your praiſe) ſurely you haue thought of that ſame old ſaying of yours; <hi>If I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not mooue the gods aboue, I will trouble the diuels below.</hi> So your workes are vnprofitable, and the worke of iniquity is in your hands: your feete doe runne to miſchiefe, and doe make haſt to ſpill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood. Theſe are the things which haue cauſed you to be baniſhed.</p>
            <p>For what would it haue beene, if the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians</hi> or <hi>Hungarians,</hi> ſhould haue contended
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22038:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> any longer with words? They ſaid with <hi>Cato,</hi> moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the reproaches of a certaine man; we haue an vnequall condition of ſtriuing with you: for as it is moſt eaſie for you to ſpeake ill, and to heare ill; ſo it is vnpleaſant to vs to ſpeake ill, and vnaccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to heare ill. But get yee gone rather yee <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> neuer returne into theſe Kingdomes. So the daies of the wicked ſhall be ſhortned. And what other remedy is there? <hi>Agar</hi> and her ſonne <hi>Iſmael</hi> attempted to ſtirre vp ſtrife, diſſenſions and contentions, alſo to ſow the greateſt diſcord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sara.</hi> Can a wiſe father of a family winke at theſe things? he can neuer doe it: rather let him caſt out the bondwoman with her ſon. Which thing is done; who can ſay it is ill done? furthermore the <hi>Bohemians</hi> are not priuy to any fault in your ſetting forth of ſhowes: vnleſſe happily paſſing by, they appoint a popular action againſt the act of eiection and baniſhment: which thoſe crafty and nimble actours, and able knaues doe (we ſpeak theſe things againe (ô Fathers) leſt wee too much ſmart for them) not retained and kept in darkneſſe; but openly reſtored into the City <hi>Prague;</hi> and ſo the aire is a freſh infected. In the meane while (not nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in relating) the <hi>Bohemians</hi> doe wonder at your nimbleneſſe in dancing, accuſing nature that ſhee made not you actors and tumblers. The report go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth (for what do we ſtanding any longer vpon theſe) that in times paſt chaſtity and continency were amongſt the Catholike brethren: wee beleeue it,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22038:12"/> but in that age: when innocency was honored, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity extolled; and pouerty eſteemed: now what ſinke is not more cleane then this ſtate of Prieſts? yee are truly the Fathers of your country: the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians</hi> haue found your key which you haue loſt or laid aſide: they now behold your effeminate appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell and houſhold ſtuffe. Thus they ſee, and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee now that which ſo many religious men of you haue locked vp, who are whoremongers, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, lewd perſons, Sodomiticall, Parricides, murtherers of Kings, diſdainefull, warre-makers, Atheiſts, Epicures, malefactors, truce-breakers, tyrants, in a word, who are all wickedneſſe. Ye ſhall know them by their fruites, as it is written. Where you intrude your ſelues, you make your ſelues Lords; theſe, ſeruants, which the Preacher foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſaith; I ſaw the ſeruants riding, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces walking on foot, like ſeruants. Marriages alſo are contracted amongſt ſome (of which you are the authors) without the conſent of parents: they talke of this in euery towne, village, and company in <hi>Flanders, Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany.</hi> You ſteale away their eldeſt ſonnes; <hi>France</hi> doth witneſſe this. You take away their onely ſonnes from their Parents, that yee may afterward be poſſeſſors of their goods, and ſo relieue and help your owne companies. And this is your ſure <hi>Vulcans</hi> ſhield; by which you were ſo noted, that <hi>Spaine</hi> did vrge you to change theſe your wicked practiſes; that the elders of the families might be ſecure from your inuations.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:22038:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> (I beleeue) foreknewe this your religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſaying, Many doe feare an ill report, fewe an ill conſience. But you deale warily, in that you are not aſhamed to teach openly, that you are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to no gouernment in the world but to the Sea of Rome. Who therefore ſhall iudge you in theſe coaſts? Shall the Pope? Vnleſſe the <hi>Bohemians</hi> and <hi>Hungarians</hi> by chance doe come betweene: You teach the youth for nothing; but for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? This appeares by your Religious houſes; by the moſt Princely and ſtately Theaters in them: on which you haue Comedies acted, ful of a poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or Heatheniſh delights; How faith is not to be kept with Heretikes; How Euangelicall faith is to be rooted out with <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> and ſuch like things, that you may bee the better emboldned, you ſpend whole daies with your Scholers in theſe delights &amp; pleaſures; and the nights alſo doe you paſſe ouer on this wiſe: you are become ſo brazen faced through theſe your doings, that ſhortly you may learne to bee quite ſhameleſſe. Hence it is no maruell that you are Winebibbers, Effeminate, ſtately, and full of money. Your Schollers bring you Gold as much as they can; that they may neuer ouerloade you. Is vertue to begotten after money? Wee let paſſe to ſpeake of your companions in certaine well ordered Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; that one example of Father <hi>Swares</hi> ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice you, which we commit to your moyſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in theſe things. But who are they whom you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22038:13"/> teach for nothing? Are they poore? truely no; they are Heires of great riches and large Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions. Theſe will not ſuffer your Society to want for riches. We wonder that you know not theſe things. You know many things, and doe you not know your ſelues? The ſumme of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy bids; Know thy ſelfe. So no man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how much he knoweth not. You read <hi>Danus</hi> in <hi>Terence,</hi> but you doe not ſee how you diſturbe and confound all things. You reade of the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants in <hi>Virgill;</hi> but how you your ſelues doe wage Warre with heauen and all the gods, you doe not know. You reade of the <hi>Cyclops</hi> in <hi>Euripides;</hi> but you ſee not how you feare neither God nor man. Truely it is more then Cymmerian darkneſſe you are in; vnleſſe you happily imitate <hi>Socrates,</hi> who knew onely this, that he knew nothing. But why doe wee proſequte theſe things with ſtile and words? One thing we adde of thoſe huge ones, before we bring in the Concluſion. You Ieſuits were meere Aeoluſes, who ſent your boyſterous Northerne and Eaſterne windes vpon this age, and the whole Romane Empire: that you might onely obtaine the moſt curſed ende of your Sect; namely, the Monarchie of the whole world, and ſubiect all the Kingdomes of the World to the Sea of Rome. Hence doe troubles compaſſe vs about like vnto <hi>Numida,</hi> and new waues amongſt the ſurges. O when ſhall wee be in that pure and certaine calme, which you haue couered with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22038:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> clowdes, that ſhortly will cauſe a tempeſt. The aſhes which you ſpread abroad ſeeme to returne to you, ready to burne vp your Society. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture ſaith, <hi>In the multiplying of the wicked, wickedneſſe ſhall be multiplyed, and the iuſt ſhall ſee their falles.</hi> But that wee may make an ende of theſe things which we ſay by the report of others, do not thinke (O Fathers Ieſuits) that wee would hurt any of your Society hereby; for they are not ours: but ſuch as long ſince were obiected againſt you by the whole world: which things, becauſe you haue not anſwered; I thought good to mooue, not for vpbrayding, but for conference ſake.</p>
            <p>It is not poſſible (me thinke) that Religion and ſo many wickedneſſes ſhould dwell together in one Colledge: which if you ſhould ſuffer to reſide vpon you, ſurely we would ſay that you are the worſt of all that goe on two feete: whoſe bodies are hardened with ſo many skarres of villany and wickedneſſes, that there is no roome for another ſtroke. But, though we knowe no other by you, yet we hope better. For whither you goe; you immitate the Nouenſilian gods. Doe you make ſpeeches? your lippes are beſmeered with <hi>Cicero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> eloquence. Doe you laugh? the Graces ſeem to be in your eyes. Doe you pray? All the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs are beheld in your countenances. Doe yee line? you are chaſter then the Monkes of <hi>Syria,</hi> called Eſcenor: ſo that if you ſhould chance to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22038:14"/> ſee dogges and bitches together in the ſtreet you would turne away your faces like <hi>Clotomicus;</hi> for they that haue honeſt mindes haue tender fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, as <hi>Simocus</hi> writeth. You are more abſtinent from Wine, then <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> ſometime Biſhop of <hi>Ruſpanary:</hi> you doe almoſt go beyond <hi>Elias</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Wilderneſſe neere the Brooke <hi>Carith.</hi> What are <hi>Paul</hi> the firſt Hermit, <hi>Antony, Hillarion, Patroclus;</hi> and others, in their auſtere ſolitarie liues, which are mariages in reſpect of your auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity? Will the world needs be deceiued? Let it be gulled, we ſpeake ſparingly of your praiſes, leſt thoſe truthes we tell ſhould be blotted with a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition of flattery: we could not chuſe but ſet down the things fore-mentioned that it might appeare what opinion Germany hath of you, and that we might hold you no longer pining in ſuſpence of expectation, if you be not guilty of the aforeſaide knaueries, ſurely there muſt be ſome ſecret auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, or contrarietie of nature which made theſe Countries ſpue ye out, as ſome mens ſtomacks do Cheeſe, or Fiſh, or Oyle, which proceeds not of any known cauſe, but from a certaine Antipothy of nature: wherof in imitation of <hi>Marſhial</hi> the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et we may ſay:
<q>
                  <l>I loue thee not O Ieſuite,</l>
                  <l>The cauſe thereof I cannot write:</l>
                  <l>But this I wot, I loue thee not.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Graue Fathers we can ſay no more to this vnles there be ſome ſtrange &amp; hidden diſeaſe in yee: tis
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22038:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> wonderful what ſhould be the reaſon why all true <hi>Germaines</hi> ſhould openly profeſſe, that all Cities &amp; Townes are deſperatly ſick wher ther be any neſts of <hi>Ieſuits:</hi> ſurely there muſt be ſome contagious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeas that ſtickes to your Companies, or els you are tormented with ſome other maladies of the Stone or burning Feauers, or turmoiling of your loynes, els why are found in your Coleges, ſuch groaning chaires as women vſe in Child-birth. <hi>Homer</hi> tels of of one that was angry becauſe <hi>Thirſites</hi> ſate in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel among the Princes, &amp; ſhall we be ſo patient to ſuffer thoſe to dwell among vs that are ouerrunne with I know not what ſcuruy foule euill? Surely, it were fitter that all of your ranke were ſwept out of al <hi>Germany,</hi> then be let in adores where they haue bin once fairely rid of ye. Why ſhould <hi>Germany</hi> let ye ſet footing in more places then ye haue already, the Moniſtary which you ſeeke are profitable for our Churches &amp; ſchooles which are not to be rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed that you might enioy them. It ſhould go very hard with vs if your Lettine ſhould bee ſong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, we mean that Letany by which ye ſong to death two <hi>Popes, Clement</hi> the <hi>8.</hi> who in the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation concerning <hi>Grace</hi> did ſet you out in your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours; and <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fift who was your profeſſed enemy: if ye will not deale ſo with vs, we will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford ye our counſell and helpe, but vpon this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that ye keepe your ſelues within the limits of your Schooles, and affect not heereafter the intermedling of State matters.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:22038:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> might bee your Prtrone, who though he were a man made of the beſt moulde, yet often wiſhed his own quiet &amp; deſired to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant from the affaires of gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that he might liue to himſelfe, and to the Muſes: why ſhould not your great ſpirits doe ſo? and let Kings handle their owne Scepters: whileſt yee ſtriue to clime thus high, yee make your ſelues ridiculous. Keepe your ſelues in the middle courſe, hold yee to your owne ſtation; that is, read Grammer to young youthes: It was good aduiſe giuen of olde;
<q>
                  <l>That which thou art deſire to be,</l>
                  <l>And wiſh not other lotte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to thee.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The place which yee are to be ſent, muſt be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to your religious Sect, ſuch a one we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto you, being very fit for your Confeſſion and whole courſe of life. We haue found a place where you may haue your Schoole, your Innes, your Hoſpitals, your Priſons, your Chayres, your Churches and places of Confeſſion: heere yee may exerciſe your faſting and ſeuereſt diſcipline, or rather a temperate and medecinall diet; if your iollity heere be ouer clowded ſome time with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, you muſt remember how braue a thing it is to beare ſtripes manfully, but you will aske where this religious holy place is, whither wee would ſend yee, it is in <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in the Low countries, the Saint that is worſhiped in this religious and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22038:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> miraculus place is called Saint <hi>Rorſpine,</hi> and his Colledge that is ioyned with them is Saint <hi>Ponus,</hi> the place is ſittuate in the way nere the holy ſtreet, and becauſe you loue holeſome Ayre well: heere is that admirable good temper of the Ayre which can neuer be expreſt, though a man hard as many tongues as there be flies in <hi>Armenia,</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> by reaſon of the ſea incompaſſing and interlacing, there is perpetuall trafficke, ſo that hereby ye may haue opportunitie to doe that which Ieſuits much buſie themſelues withall; namely to ſend and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue daily intelligence from farre Countries, this is a fayre pull for you, but yet there is more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind: our Maiſters of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> are ſomewhat ouerhoneſt, and eaſily taken with men that make profeſſion of religious order, and by reaſon of the monſtrous miracles that are daily performed, they giue very large offerings to this ſaint <hi>Rorſpine</hi> and his fellow; they ceaſe not euery day to offer vp moſt precious Francomſcence to this god, and to account his Prieſt the toppe of their friends, and becauſe they know that yee loue faire and large houſes, they promiſe that if this houſe be to little for you, they will enlarge it, and adde other hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to it; and all for Saint <hi>Rorſpine</hi> ſake, and Saint <hi>Ponus,</hi> and for the Brother-hood of the Ieſuits: and heere might yee haue good opportunity to ſpread your Religion and inſtructions, for that many that haue a Catholike vaine are brought dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Amſterdam</hi> by wooden horſes, who would
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22038:16"/> acount it great gaine for them that you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into Saint <hi>Rorſpines</hi> ſanctuary, and there ye ſhould be rid of the daily feare of being baniſhed or being torne aſunder like <hi>Acteon</hi> with his Doggs. If yee haue any ſecret diſeaſe which yee would be aſhamed to confeſſe in the Temple of <hi>Eſculapius,</hi> yee may be bould with this <hi>Saint,</hi> who will be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to heale your ſores if yee ſhall doe thus, and ply the people as they ſhalbe ſent to your ſchoole, yee may laughe at the great Statſe-men that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered by the factions of the people, and are faine to fiſh with a golden hooke, whileſt your ſelues ſit quiet in the middeſt of all ſtormes. And now there ſhall be no more Pilgrimages taken to our Ladie of <hi>Loretto,</hi> or of <hi>Hales,</hi> ſaint <hi>Rorſpine</hi> ſhall take vp all the cuſtome, that ſhall robbe all other ſhrines of miracles, there ſhal we heare how many hath beene healed by the power of ſaint <hi>Rorſpine,</hi> by the interceſſion of ſaint <hi>Ponus,</hi> here was one freed from a burning Ague, there another burſten guts healed: <hi>Iohn Fuks</hi> a ſouldier of Scotland reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his health by ſingular deuotion and ceaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe praier. <hi>Francis Roſſe</hi> at <hi>Anwerpe</hi> was in the like manner cured of a dangerous melancholly diſeaſe by the ſame interceſſion: Another like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of a lame Creeple was made as nimple as a dauncer: Another voyded a worme out of his body of a huge length. And this ſame ſaint <hi>Rorſpin</hi> in the yeare 1610. did cure a certaine Iriſhman of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22038:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Falling ſickneſſe, and caſt a Diuell out of a woman at <hi>Lewarden.</hi> Nay, the very name of ſaint <hi>Rorſpine</hi> being vttered in the hearing of the ſicke will make them as whole as a Fiſh. In the yeare 1602. when the plague was ſo ripe in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> it neuer touched this holy place, the inhabiters thereof were in ſo good health, that their skinnes were ſo full as they could hold for cracking: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe, many Miracles are done in <hi>France, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> but there a man muſt beleeue them, and make himſelfe blinde to ſee them. But our Saints Miracles doth bulke vp a Gods name, though a man hath no beliefe in them, there remaine viſible euidences of them which hang vp in the Church of Fame. And that we be not ſilent of the houſes prouided for our Fathers the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> the houſe prouided for them is a faire Pallace, the Roofe of it is couered with Braſſe, the Pauement of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Porfree Chechered in diuers colours, wherein are artificially ingrauen the ſtory of all their Miracles, a ſtately Vaile is ſuſtained with three Pillers, betweene which runneth a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whoſe water guſheth out through the throat of a ſeuen headed Hydra. Here may the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> inioy all thoſe recreations and pleaſures which their minds or bodies incline vnto: haſte your ſelues hither Iolly Fathers, the <hi>Amſterdamians</hi> do erneſtlie looke for your comming, St. <hi>Rorſpine</hi> and Saint <hi>Ponus</hi> expect your ſeruice, make no delay to hoiſe vp Saile for <hi>Amſterda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> good fortune wil blow
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22038:17"/> a full gale in the poope of your feruent deſires.</p>
            <p>They ended their ſpeach, &amp; the good Fathers the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> wold haue bin weeping ripe at theſe words, but that there faces are made of Bell-mettell, they ſet a good face on it, and deuoure their griefe, and with a ſeeming good courage proclaime that they are all for St. <hi>Rorſpine;</hi> they truſſe vp their Trinkets, and prouide for <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> three daies hence they take Waggon where they ſit fixe of them, by two and two; their moſt nimble &amp; officious Waggo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is <hi>Arnold</hi> the Aduocate of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> he that made the famous Oration in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> he gets vp with the whip in his hand, and layes about him ſo luſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he flies with his luggage through the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, the people that ſee this Chariot ſcoure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long ſo faſt, giue many reaſons of this gallopping; the wiſeſt among them ſay, that <hi>Arnolt</hi> makes this haſte with his carriage, leſt perhaps theſe Fathers ſhould ſneake away and goe into <hi>France,</hi> and there not onely ſwarme in the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> Colleges, but alſo creepe into the Kings Court and Counſell, and ſo domineere that no man dare open his lippes againſt them. Thus the Ieſuites flew out of the countrey as it were with the wings of <hi>Peggaſus,</hi> and no maruell, for no man would hold vp his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to ſtay them, whether Papiſt or Proteſtant. The Superior Commanders among the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> rid thus in pompe, but the ordinary frye of them did laky it out on foot, and carried euery one his pack
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22038:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> at his backe, and theſe were as proud as their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that ridde, and would be thought to imitate the Apoſtles: and as they went in Proceſſion, they chaunted a Letany to ſaint <hi>Rorſpine</hi> making the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdum of their ſong, <hi>Nunc dimittis Seruos tuos Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine:</hi> whereto <hi>Germany</hi> ſung an Ecco, <hi>Iuſta ſunt iuditia tua Domine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I haue deliuered in briefe, the relation of the ſending of the Ieſuites of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary</hi> on a long arrante to Saint <hi>Rorſpine;</hi> whereto I adde nothing elſe but that it is hoped that all <hi>Germany</hi> wil furniſh their Waggons with all their Ieſuits to follow their Fellowes on this iourney: the eyes of great many of the greateſt haue bene long time hoodwinked, and the darke night caſt ouer them, but now that vaile vaniſheth and cleare light ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, diſcouereth the danger which hangeth ouer the Empire, ſo that now ſmall brabling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies being laidaſide, the Princes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire wil haue an eye to the publick, &amp; foraſmuch as they ſee that all this danger and miſchiefe doth ariſe from the Ieſuites, why ſhould not they begin at the right end with caſting them out, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euident, that theſe are ſpies and vnderminers for the aduancing the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarchy? Why ſhould they not be more iealous of them then of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. <hi>Spaine</hi> boaſteth that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the Weſt is due to them by deſtinie, vpon this hope, they which had their beginnings from the Mores and Sarizens, goe on to worke their
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22038:18"/> owne ends by their bloudy Inquiſitions. This creeping Gangreine muſt be cut off leſt it grow to farre in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> in <hi>Italy, France</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> What Priuy Counſels of State are there in <hi>Germany</hi> vnreuealed to the <hi>Spaniard?</hi> Where hath he not in other countries his Penſioners for intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and his partie among the Counſellors of State linked to him with a golden chaine? What Diets or publike meetings haue we, the ſecrets whereof are not knowne to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> as well as to them that ſit in thoſe Parliaments? A thing moſt pernicious to our States, and diſhonourable to the name of <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Prince or people is there of the reformed Religion, whom the <hi>Spaniard</hi> doth not thinke he hath as iuſt cauſe to ruine, as to quell the Turkes or Pagans? Nor is this iuſt feare to be found in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, but it concernes them alſo that are pure Roman Catholikes. Were not the <hi>Fredirankes, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoes,</hi> and <hi>Henries,</hi> thinke you, good Catholikes? yet drunke they of this cuppe. They that will not beleeue that all the Biſhoprickes in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire were promiſed by the Spaniard to the <hi>Ieſuites.</hi> They that would rather haue the <hi>Spaniard</hi> rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them then a <hi>Caluiniſt,</hi> or <hi>Lutheran</hi> Prince, let them expect the reward which he gaue to the <hi>Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans</hi> and <hi>Portugales: Veſtram animam pertranſcibit gladius:</hi> the Ieſuites Creede is, that there is one God, one Pope, and one Catholike or Vniuerſall King.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:22038:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Be wiſe O yee Kings, yee haue an enemy as full of gold as <hi>Midas,</hi> who hath in readineſſe, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Garriſons, for any exploite thirty thouſand <hi>Spaniards,</hi> all olde beaten Souldiers. Moreouer he ſends out his Firebrandes into <hi>Europe, Affrica, Aſia</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> and into the Eaſt and Weſt Indies alſo. He commandeth <hi>Lucitanta,</hi> with the moſt fertill Iles and Kingdomes of <hi>Oceanus:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Italy,</hi> and he thirſteth after your proſperitie: Your proſperity? That ſufficeth not, but he thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth after your bloud: hee is potent. But hee will neuer diſturbe you, if theſe his grounds be broken by vnited forces. But O good God! How men are moſt ſecure in their dangerouſeſt &amp; moſt hazardableſt matters? O yee Lords &amp; Princes of the Empire, if all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> heare me, let them view with a curious eye the Lands ſituated with long diſtance of place, to which they deny paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; they cut off ayde, and doe waſte all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: this is a hard matter, but he will put to his hand againe that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> may bring forth the extreameſt of his cruelty and tyrranny, that the Subiects lamentably ſhould ſee the laſt Act of the Tragedy: whoſe heart doth ake through the feare and horror of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that they can deſire nothing but occaſion how they may gett out of this bondage into their former liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſee the <hi>Belgie</hi> deſtitute of all hope, they ſhaked off his yoake they retained the Field: let
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22038:19"/> vs ſee the Prince of <hi>Auratia:</hi> the huge number of Souldiers hee derideth and explaudeth them and their madde attempts. And that I may goe no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (o Princes and Peeres) who are yee? are yee not <hi>Germaines?</hi> ſurely altogether the ſame. Now the dignitie and power of the Germaine Empire is not to be meaſured, by the greatnes of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and people but by the vnited faith, power and fortitude; by theſe (but what doe I ſtand to ſay it) you ſhall ouercome the Kingdomes of the whole world if yee be of one mind; I ſay your dignitie (oh yee Peeres of the Germaine Empire) and power are mightie if they be vnited. Oh yee States of the Empire, doe not ſuffer that Heroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call vertue and thoſe deuine forces to bee extinct in the Germaynes: by which yee haue tamed the whole World, but exerciſe your valiant breaſtes and vnconquered ſtrength againſt theſe Maſſing Prieſtes; and doe yee all meete and agree in one holy league againſt your profeſſed and ſworne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, if any generoſitie or courrage remaine in you, ſhew it, but if otherwiſe, I, like another Cynicke, will laffe at your ſluggiſhnes and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorgie: and will ſay, that I cride out in vaine to this age, which hath a great number of ſleepers and very few wakers: heare a parradox, I will giue you a great precept if you will remaine great, <hi>Cauete, Conſulite, Vigilate,</hi> this is only neſceſſary in this age, <hi>Hoc agite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou in the meane while good and courtious
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22038:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> Reader be fauorable, and fare thou well, if there be any pleaſant ſpeech let it redound to our loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Country, and alſo to thy pleaſant and fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable iudgement, in the meane time doe not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme and thinke it my purpoſe to ſpeake of any Claſſicke thing to wheet one and ſtire vp the Profeſſors of the Goſpell againſt the Catholikes; to adde fewell to that publike fier; I haue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther minde that the ſweetenes of concord might ſhine betweene the Profeſſors of the Goſpell and the Catholikes in this Empire: which the Ieſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and Spaniſh Clowdes haue not only obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but almoſt extinguiſhed, theſe Ieſuitticall and Spaniſh wickedneſſes, haue drawne the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from me againſt my will; we vnfainedly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace theſe ſincere affection of the reſt of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes in this Empire, and with our vnited and conioyned forces (as it becommeth bretheren in one Land,) wee doe ſeeke remedy for theſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like euils; I did write with a troubled penne, in a troubleſome yeare: wherein we ſee that good men are preſſed downe and euill men ſet vp, and wicked men preſſed downe and good men ſet vp.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
